An American legend comes to life.
Pocahontas is a adventure, animation, family film directed by Mike Gabriel.
Pocahontas, daughter of a Native American tribe chief, falls in love with an
English soldier as colonists invade 17th century Virginia.
Pocahontas (voice), played by Irene Bedard.
John Smith (voice), played by Mel Gibson.
Governor Ratcliffe (voice), played by David Ogden Stiers.
Meeko (voice), played by John Kassir.
Thomas (voice), played by Christian Bale.
Pocahontas (singing voice), played by Judy Kuhn.
Pocahontas is a 1995 American animated musical historical drama film loosely based on the life of
Powhatan woman Pocahontas and the arrival of English settlers from the Virginia Company.
It was directed by Mike Gabriel and Eric Goldberg from a screenplay
written by Carl Binder, Susannah Grant, and Philip LaZebnik.
Produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation, the film romanticizes Pocahontas's
encounter with John Smith and her legendary saving of his life.
The film stars the voices of Irene Bedard and Mel Gibson as Pocahontas and Smith,
respectively, with David Ogden Stiers, Russell Means, Christian Bale, Michelle St.
John, James Apaumut Fall, Billy Connolly, Joe Baker, Gordon
Tootoosis, and Linda Hunt in supporting roles.
The score was composed by Alan Menken, who also wrote the
film's songs with lyricist Stephen Schwartz.
After making his directorial debut with The Rescuers Down Under (1990),
Gabriel conceived the film during a Thanksgiving weekend.
Goldberg, who had just finished up work as the supervising animator of the
Genie in Aladdin (1992), joined Gabriel as co-director.
The project went into development concurrently with The Lion King
(1994), and attracted most of Disney's top animators.
Meanwhile, Disney studio chairman Jeffrey Katzenberg decided that the film should be an emotional romantic epic in the vein of Beauty
and the Beast (1991), in hope that like Beauty, it would also be nominated for the Academy Award for Best Picture.
Screenwriters Binder, Grant, and LaZebnik took creative liberties with
history in an attempt to make the film palatable to audiences.
Pocahontas premiered at Central Park on June 10, 1995, and was released in the United States on June 16, to mixed reactions from critics and
audiences, who praised its animation, voice performances, and music, but criticized its story with its lack of focus on tone.
The film's historical inaccuracies and artistic
license received polarized responses.
Pocahontas earned over $346 million at the box office.
The film received two Academy Awards for Best Musical or Comedy Score for
Menken and Best Original Song for "Colors of the Wind".
According to critics, the depiction of Pocahontas as an empowered heroine
influenced subsequent Disney films like Mulan (1998) and Frozen (2013).
The film was followed by a direct-to-video sequel,
Pocahontas II: Journey to a New World, in 1998.
The film explores themes of princess, culture clash, cartoon, villain, colony.
The tone is emotional.